[Music]
Hey, hey,
hey, hey.
[Music]
Well, good morning everyone and welcome
to the Fiber Broadband Association's
five for breakfast. We're now in our
30th episode of 2025 and before we kick
off, I'd like to thank Wesco, the
platinum sponsor of Fiber for Breakfast.
Well, a lot is going on in Washington
DC. At NTI earlier this week, all 56
states and territories initial proposals
received the green light from NTI,
allowing them to advance to the benefit
of the bargain round, a critical step in
the BE application process under the
revised guidance. Final proposals are
due to NTI by September 4th. You know,
yesterday NTI hosted a virtual public
listening session titled Bolstering Data
Center Growth, Resiliency, and Security.
And the purpose of the listening session
uh was to seek input from a wide range
of stakeholders to inform an upcoming
NTI report outlining the challenges and
opportunities to data center growth,
resiliency, and security. So, I
delivered brief remarks emphasizing the
critical importance of access to fiber
in powering the next generation
technologies. Um, I really enjoyed Zo's
uh testimony where they explained how
critical it is to have fiber off and on
ramps for uh for AI to rural communities
to avoid what they call death loops,
which is when a rural community um are
not able to participate in the AI future
to lack of fiber connectivity.
So, in Congress, Ariel Roth is expected
to be confirmed as soon as this morning
as the NTI administrator and assistant
secretary of commerce. We look forward
to working with her as she takes on this
new leadership role at NTI. At the FCC,
uh they'll have their next open meeting
tomorrow where commissioners will vote
on a draft of their network
modernization NPRM notice of proposed
rulemaking. Uh FBA has been reviewing
the draft of their members to assess its
potential impact. You know, last week we
held an amazing regional fiberconnect
workshop in Anchorage, Alaska. You know,
it's clear that Alaska is unlike any
other state or territory in our nation.
You know, Alaska is twice the size of
Texas, but only has a population of
740,000 people versus 30 million in
Texas. Further, Alaska's topology is
quite diverse with lots of islands,
mountains, and tundra, not to mention a
very short build window. We learned a
lot from Thomas Lochner, the uh the
state's broadband director, who
described the challenging topology and
remoteness of the state's unserved and
underserved locations. More importantly,
we learned that in Alaska,
communications are life and death. You
know, there's no golden hour for
emergency rescues, and we greatly
appreciate the warm reception received
during our visit to the 49th state. We
will continue our road show in the Great
White North. We'll be in Toronto on
Tuesday, August 19th. We hopefully see
you there.
After Toronto, we'll be in Spokane on
September, Scottsdale in October, Kansas
City in November, and then we'll finish
here in Palm Springs um in December 8th
and 9th for our premier member meeting.
Today on fire for breakfast, our um
guest is Gav Juna, the chief operating
officer, Consolidate Communications,
discuss Fidium's transformation or
transforms New England's future with
fiber. Before I introduce today's guest,
I'd like to introduce David Norris from
our team who's going to walk us through
some housekeeping items.
>> Thank you very much, Gary, and thank you
to everyone who's joining us this
morning. Good morning. Before I go over
a few logistics, we'd like to once again
thank our platinum sponsor, Fiber for
Breakfast Wesco. Now, as participants,
you are in listenon mode today. However,
we want to hear from you. To ask a
question, please type it into the
question box, which is located in the
lower lefth hand side of your screen. We
will host a Q&A session with our
panelists at the end of today's
presentation. This presentation is also
being recorded and will be available on
FBA's website within 24 to 48 hours and
you can find that recording in the
events tab under the fiber for breakfast
dropdown option. Finally, at the
conclusion of today's webinar, you'll be
prompted to complete a brief feedback
survey. If you could take a moment to do
so, your responses really help us out
and we appreciate your input. And with
that, I will hand things back over to
Gary to once again get us started. Gary.
>> Thanks Dave and good morning. I'm Gary
Bolton, the president CEO of the Fiber
Broadband Association. Last week on Fire
for Breakfast, our guest was Al Alisa uh
Kennedy, the state broadband and digital
equity director for public service
commission of Wisconsin discuss
continuing to connect Wisconsin
strategies for statewide broadband
access. So Lisa shared with us where
they are with respect to their bead
process and next steps for Wisconsin. So
if you missed it, you can go to our
website and watch the replay. Today on
fire for breakfast our guest is Gav Juna
the chief operating officer at
consolidated communications who's going
to discuss Fidium's trans how fidium
transforms New England's future with
fiber. So G is the chief operating
officer at Consolidated and oversees the
Fidium consumer fiber business including
market development, product management,
marketing sales, call centers, customer
experience, base management as well as
field operations and information
technology. which supports enterprise.
So basically he does everything and G
joined the company in 2023 as president
of consolidated consumer and small
business organization.
Prior to joining the company, G served
as executive vice president and GM for
consumer and chief revenue officer at
Metronet where he was responsible for
building all consumer sales channels,
marketing, product management, MDU,
market expansion, customer care and
sales operation. As EV uh EVP of
consumer at Metronut, he led product
management, customer care and field
marketing. Junja al also held leadership
positions at rise broadband dish
networks and RJ group of companies a
retailer for T-Mobile and Sprint where
he led consumer and SMB sales channels
field marketing and overall go to market
strategy. Gorav has an MBA from Cornell
University and a BA from Trinity
College. So welcome G and for audience
please type in your questions you go and
we'll work those into the discussion. So
with that I will turn things over to G.
You bet, Gary. Thank you. Pleasure to be
here and really appreciate the
opportunity for uh Consolidated Infidium
to share our story. Um so that said,
I'll get right into it. Um this is an
overview on Consolidated and our fiber
brand specifically within Consolidated
is known as Fidian. So during this
presentation, you will see me refer to
our fiber business as Fidian. Um, all of
that to say, when you think about our
core business, our mission at
Consolidated is to bring broadband
infrastructure to unserved and
underserved communities throughout our
footprint. And we truly believe that
broadband infrastructure uh enables
people to live, work, and thrive in
communities, specifically underserved
and unserved communities, just so they
don't have to just so they don't have to
relocate um into urban centers. So we're
committed to the mission and what you
will see throughout uh this presentation
is that we have partnered with state
broadband offices, cities,
municipalities to again take broadband
infrastructure to these unserved
communities.
Consolidated has three different
business segments consumer, commercial
and carrier. So we will not go into a
town or a city just with one business
segment or one customer segment. We will
go in with all three. And that again
goes back to our mission of providing
critical broadband infrastructure for
rural communities to thrive. So a
consumer business, we have 2.6 million
passes as you'll see on this map. We we
have 2.6 million passes across the
country which is a combination of both
copper and fiber. We have upgraded more
than 50% 54% to be specific of our plant
to fiber. So that and that's currently
the case at 1.4 4 million passes with a
long-term goal of being an 80% plus
fiberized company which means that we
will have more than two million passes
on fiber by the end of 2027 or somewhere
in the range of 2028.
Um that's our story on consumer fiber.
We also again as I mentioned have a very
deep and thriving commercial business
and have a very deep and thriving
carrier business. And this goes back to
our philosophy of if rural communities
need to thrive, we don't just take our
residential or our consumer business
there. We go out to small businesses, we
go to hospitals, municipalities,
schools, and we provide commercial
services along with carrier circuits.
And 80% of our fiber circuits are unique
in the towns that we serve. So with that
said, um
I'll talk about our evolution. Back in
2020, only 11% of our footprint was
covered in fiber. When we think we
launched Fidium Fiber as our fiber brand
in 2021
and we have a new we have an investor,
we had investors at the time. We were a
publicly traded company. In December of
2024, we uh we went private. So our
investor and our partner search light
capital um who they were a great partner
even when we were a public company but
since we've been private again as I
mentioned we've upgraded more than 50%
of our plant to fiber with the goal to
be at 80%. and or 80% plus. And when
when you really think about our
long-term vision, which again is very
much uh in play, we are going to have a
futurep proof uh infrastructure which is
not only complemented with fiber
technology but a seamless customer
experience. And we truly believe that we
have put customers now at the heart of
every single thing that we do. We've
digitized the customer experience. We've
simplified processes. We've rationalized
the product portfolio. All of that to
say we truly want to be a nextgen fiber
company and we're well on our way.
Um our strategy is very simple. It's
hard to execute the strategy, but when I
think about the three legs of the stool
on the strategy again as I mentioned,
number one, it's about having the
fastest and the most reliable network in
the markets that we serve. And again,
the markets that we serve are more
underserved than more unserved and
underserved.
We want to and we are delivering an
exceptional customer experience. And
that's just not that's not just um
talking to a customer care
representative or talking to a tech
support uh representative. It's really a
culture across the organization where we
are customer first. And that just means
we put the customer even in a legal
contract, even in a vendor contract. We
want to make sure we're always thinking
about the customer experience. And then
last but not the least, we have
significantly as a telco, we have
significantly simplified our operations.
And in in the operations, I specifically
I'm talking about people. We're hiring
people that bring value and that again
will enable this this u uh exceptional
customer experience. I'm talking about
processes dramatically simplifying them
and for both time um to serve the
customer and for cost to serve the
customer. And then I'm talking about um
uh products. We've simplified our
product portfolio. So we when we go into
a city or a town again we're going in
with a multi-prong and a multi
multicustomer approach. Residential
customers, small and medium businesses,
enterprise businesses and and and
customers who want their own dedicated
circuits. So we've simplified the
product portfolio to cater to all
different customer segments and to do it
expeditiously.
Um really when I think about when I
think about our strengths at
consolidated that we have built it comes
down to five things. We believe we have
a unique and natural asset and I'll talk
about that. We have a proven
construction engine and again as I
mentioned 1.4 4 million which is 54% of
our footprint is already covered in
fiber with 80% or higher being the goal.
Um we have a proven customer acquisition
engine. So this is an execution muscle
that we have built over the last two
years and it continues to get stronger
year-over-year. Um where I've talked
about the exceptional customer
experience and I'll I'll validate that
through some NPS scores. And then last
but not the least, again as I mentioned,
we truly, you know, are are overlaying
our strong consumer business with a very
very robust and thriving commercial and
carrier business. So when I think about
us having a unique and natural asset, we
70% of our fiber build is happening in
Northern New England and in Northern New
England 90% of our plant is aerial. With
the aerial plant and the fact that we
have joint ownership of these poles, we
have unencumbered access to these poles
and because of our commercial business
and our carrier business, we have a
large core dense fiber network which is
the middle mile network. So, not only do
we have aerial infrastructure and access
to our pools for our last mile network,
we also have a large core dense dense
network for our middle mile network. And
as a result, what that gives us is
predictability of speed to build and
cost to build. We could literally um we
could literally work with a town and
choose and decide to build the town and
actually have it built within four to
six months. And there's again this
predictability of speed and cost versus,
you know, typically for any for anybody
else to go and build that town, it would
historically take them anywhere in the
range of 12 to 18 months, especially for
an aerial plant. All of that to say, we
believe we give customers predictability
and we believe we can get into a town,
choose to build a town and build it fast
and build it very economically.
What that then gives us is a robust
fiber construction engine. And I think
the big thing to point out here on this
slide and my big takeaway in this slide
is if you look at what we built in 2022,
we built 400,000 passes fiber passes in
the second year of our fiber build. And
again, from my experience or my past
experience as a fiber overbuilder, it
takes a long time to build 400,000
passes in one given year. All of this to
prove that we have the capability, we
have the speed to build a lot of fiber
passes and we're going to continue to do
that. And as I mentioned at the
beginning of the presentation that 2
million, we're going to be a fiber
provider with two million passes um that
will be fiberized across our eight state
footprint with 70% of it in Northern New
England.
So, you know, the question is with
Northern New England, what have we done?
And when I think about Northern New
England, we have part we have
specifically partnered with the Coods in
Vermont. And we've partnered with the
city, the c the county, and the state
broadband office in Maine and New
Hampshire. And again, we have taken
service to these unserved to unserved
and underserved communities where
typically fiber infrastructure would be
hard to take um and take uh uh
infrastructure to. We have worked with
those city and state broadband offices
to take our infrastructure to these
towns. And I'm incredibly proud of this.
The reason being is I truly believe that
rural communities are compared to the
larger urban centers are considered the
underdog. And I truly believe when I
think about the best stories and the
most inspiring stories when it comes to
communities or comes to sports or teams,
it all starts with being the underdog.
Point being is we're providing critical
infrastructure. We're doing it in
conjunction with these state and
broadband offices. And we're incredibly
we're incredibly proud to be the
provider of choice in these towns where
people don't need to relocate to biggest
to bigger centers to bigger urban
centers to realize what I believe is
their American dream, which is to get
their dream job, to get a quality
education, to get access to health care,
to get opportunity. they don't have to
move to larger towns because of the
fiber infrastructure that we provide.
And I want to sincerely thank the states
that have partnered with us and the
cities and the counties that have
partnered with us to provide this
critical infrastructure to these rural
communities.
So you know next up is providing
critical infrastructure is one thing but
then providing an exceptional customer
experience is is another thing and this
is the execution muscle that we have
built. you know, our NPS, our combined
NPS score across all our customer
interactions is at a 45. That is
dramatically higher than the cable goes.
And quite candidly, I believe that we're
just scratching the surface. I truly
believe that our goal is to be at 70 um
for NPS and that is very possible with
some of the initiatives that we are
undertaking. We have something called
the Fidia promise. It's all about making
sure that you can service customers
expeditious expeditiously on installs
and on repairs. It's making sure that
when you provide service to customers,
that service is certified by a
technician. It's really making sure that
your IT stack and your digital your your
experience is fully digitized. So when
customers call you for anything, there's
a single pane of glass where you know
the records are kept in one place and
they have immediate access to everything
that they need. All of that to say, we
truly believe that from an NPS
standpoint, we're already beating the
competition and we believe we're
scratching the surface.
I'm sorry. Um, so we talked a lot about
we talked a lot about the consumer
business, NPS. I've talked about how our
commercial and our carrier business is a
really strong overlay. In fact, if
anything, consolidated actually built
that business on commercial. So what you
will see over here and as I mentioned at
the beginning, 80% of our routes are
unique and when you when I on the
carrier business and then when I think
about our commercial business, the
average lifespan of a commercial
customer in our footprint is 16 years.
So all of this to say, we've got a
thriving commercial and carrier
business. We take our commercial and
carrier business into these communities
as we launch consumer. So we have a
multi-prong approach and we're doing
this for the benefit of the community
and obviously we're doing this for the
benefit of the states that we provide
our service in.
Um, and then the last thing I'll say is
it's great to be recognized since we've
un since we've gone on this mission back
in 2021, we have been recognized by uh
entities or institutions such as CNET
that have given us awards and accolades
for the service that we've provided in
states like New Hampshire and Maine.
Again, going back to to Northern New
England, we've been recognized by uh
we've been recognized by the US
Broadband Office um again for these
public private partnerships. So, so far
in the last four years, we have
partnered with these states um and
received up to $225 million in subsidy
to go and take um our service into these
unserved and underserved communities.
And we've been, you know, given
accolades by the states. We've also been
uh you know many of our employees or our
associates have also been recognized um
for outstanding awards for service that
they've done in their communities such
as the award that you can see over there
for outstanding women in business. Um
all of this to say um we're not done
yet. We have a long way to go but we're
well on we're well on our way on this
journey to provide service to
underserved communities in Northern New
England.
Um, the last thing I'll say is clearly
our mission is to provide service to
unserved and underserved communities and
enrich how they live, work, and thrive
in their communities. And our vision is
to be America's favorite fiber provider.
And that vision can only be realized if
not not only by providing our service,
but again, it goes back to the customer
experience and really making sure that
we can delight our customers across
every interaction. So we clearly have a
mission we which we're executing. We
clearly have our vision which we're
working towards. Um and I'm just
incredibly fortunate and excited, Gary,
to be presenting our story at
Consolidated Infidium with the rest of
the fiber community.
>> Well, G um I mean you had tremendous
success at Metronet and again it looks
like Consolidated is just rocketing. Um
can you talk a little bit on your slide
six you had talked about you had
fedinium states and then some operating
states. What's the difference?
>> Uh great question. I'll pull that back
to the slide. Give me one sec. Um so our
faded states Gary are the ones in green
and that's primarily where we are
converting a majority of our or
upgrading a majority of our copper plant
to fiber. the rest of the operating
states. We we have some fiber in those
states, but they're primarily our copper
states and our voice our parts are
states where we have parts of voice
service which we're still fully which
we're absolutely fully committed to. So
that's the difference between the
operating states which is primarily
copper and parts versus the fiber states
where we're converting most of our
copper plant to fiber.
So, do you see in the future that those
would become Fidium states as well or
how do you see those?
>> Um, we're evaluating that today. Um,
Gary, we're not, you know, I can't
commit to that today. We're evaluating
that. Our goal is, you know, we clearly
have an opportunity to convert 2 million
of our 2.6 million in the states
highlighted in green. And then once we
get to and and we've evaluated that
based on the opportunity, based on our
partnership with the state um broadband
offices and with the lead opportunity
that's ahead of us also and then once
we're once we're done with that
evaluation then we'll get to the states
and blue.
>> So search light um that's a Jeep pie
right back before he went um back into
uh the association business. But um so
what was the motivation to take
consolidated private?
>> Um so a couple of different things.
Number one is just a simp number one is
uh we already search light was already
they already owned 35% when we were a
publicly traded company they owned 35%
of our shares and again as I mentioned
since 2021 and they were a great partner
uh not just in terms of capital infusion
but also in terms of expertise they've
got they have great you know uh they
have great financial partners and great
financial expertise and great operating
expertise also through their operating
partners
So we gained a lot of insight and a lot
of knowledge from them and we were
executing our our business um you know
uh planning strategically planning with
them. Um we wanted to accelerate our
fiber expansion into the states that you
know we've referenced and talked about
and we we believe that with a simplified
capital structure being private um it
would really accel it would help us
accelerate um the fiber expansion and
then since we've been private so it was
really about a simplifying the capital
structure b is the operating experience
that they were also bringing to the
table and we wanted more of that and
then c is you know since we've gone
private we've already seen the benefits
of being a private company where you
know we've u uh we've gone through a
round of ABS um uh funding and had a
very successful outcome back in May
which is again further helping us
accelerate our fiber expansion um and
you know candidly it was just drawing a
more deeper partnership with search
light who we believed again from the
first place back in 2021 was already a
great partner
>> so you know you and I have discussed
that um the private equity
It's really a robust environment for
private equity and you know private
equity's raised more money in the first
half of 2025 than all of last year for
broadband infrastructure. So why is
investing in fiber so attractive to
private equity?
>> Yeah, I think you know I think it comes
down to um I mean I can't speak for the
I can't speak for the other PE firms out
there. Um I think it is a a u I think
it's an attractive investment back again
going back to my days at Metronet now
obviously it's at um consolidated
infidium I think it's it's attractive
because you're you know your cost of cap
based on your cost of capital and then
the fiber deployment and the you know
the free cash flow that you can gain and
you know more more so the customer
benefit that you can provide and then
the free cash flow that you can gain I
think there's obviously margin over
there for the for the PE firms uh but
putting The financial piece aside, I
think it's it's really about, you know,
a providing critical infrastructure. It
goes back to the mission and that's what
really drew me in the first place to
search light and to consolidate it uh
back in 2023 which is they were very
missionoriented
and I believe that when you have a PE
firm that is thinking about financial
returns of course but is also thinking
about the mission which is providing
critical infrastructure to unserved and
underserved communities and we're very
specific uh and very targeted about who
we want to serve and then number two is
outside in addition to the mission, they
really focus on the customer experience.
And I think that when you think about
when you when we think about the
industry, we're all focusing on fiber,
which is great, but then there's also a
fair amount of customer fatigue in terms
of the experience that customers have
with, you know, um uh the incumbents. So
when you when you find when I found a PE
firm like search light that is focusing
on obviously the financial returns as I
mentioned but is more so focusing on the
mission of providing critical
infrastructure and then focusing on the
vision of being the best provider from a
customer experience standpoint. I think
that's what makes you know PE firms
really thrive and that's what's making
us with search like really thrive as
partners.
>> Yeah I mean search light great partner.
Um so it also you know we are starting
to see the beginning of a market
consolidation cycle in the fiber
industry. Um how does that fit into your
market expansion strategy?
>> We are um the good news is we're fully
we're fully committed to our you know
80% fiberization plan um and we're and
we're well funded for that um through
both debt and equity. Um so that's
obviously good news. Anything that we do
on on M&A will be incremental. So in
other words, if we can get to 90% um
fiber through M&A, um we'll be fully
committed to do so. It has to make
stretch. It has to make sense for us
strategically any M&A. In other words,
you know, we have to be able to gain
operating leverage has to be contiguous
with our foot should be hopefully
contiguous with our footprint. We have
operating leverage. We have labor we we
can gain better labor utilization,
better marketing scale. um if it makes
sense for us, I think we'll definitely
entertain that. Um but at the moment,
we're fully committed to our 80% fiber
fiber plan that does not um include any
M&A. Any M&A in the future would be um
would be incremental to our plan.
>> So you mentioned free cash flow. So,
with the uh one big beautiful bill act,
the 100% bonus depreciation,
um that's going to free up a lot of uh
free cash flow for you guys. Is that So,
how do you are you going to be putting
um 15 to 20% of that back into fiber
investment or how do you see that?
>> We we absolutely are. For for us, this
is all about the flywheel. We want to be
able to reinvest all our proceeds into
the fiber build. So we will invest our
proceeds back into fiber build back into
enabling a better customer experience.
And number three is uh enabling a much
better employee experience within the
company. Those are the three things that
we're deeply investing in.
>> All we got a bunch of audience
questions. I'm going to start with our
good friend Christine. Your plans are to
reach 80% of your locations with fiber.
What are you planning for the last 20%
and how are you going to deal with
carrier of last resort requirements for
those 20%.
>> Sure. So we we will continue to provide
our copper infrastructure for the
remaining 20%. Uh and the reason why we
can't uh the reason why we're you know
the reason why we've chosen 80% is
because we have looked at our build
across these eight states and we've
selected how we can cover how we can
ubiquitously take our coverage to this
80%. The last 20% become somewhat cost
prohibitive and that's where we're
working with the state broadband
offices. We're working on bead and
different opportunities to still be able
to take fiber if we can
opportunistically to the other 20%. But
our goal is to continue to service the
other 20% with our carbon network.
>> And then uh clarification, did you say
225 million in subsidies over five
years?
>> Over the last five years? Yes. Yes.
>> All right. Now, here's another good
question. Uh how are you managing your
workforce demand specifically with
engineering instruction given the
increased need for these resources? What
have you accomplished? And the number of
passings per year is well, what you've
accomplished is impressive. So, how are
you dealing with the workforce?
>> We we have um you know, again, as I
mentioned, we're deeply investing in our
build, our technology stack um to
provide a simplified simplified and
better customer experience. And number
three is our employee experience. So, we
are augmenting in the engineering and
construction teams. We're augmenting our
internal teams, but then we're also
contracting out. And when we contract
out both construction and engineering,
we're providing we're providing
commitments. And because we're fully
committed to this build and it's well
funded, we can actually provide those
commitments in terms of longevity uh of
work along with the dedicated rate. So
we're investing in our internal teams
through learning and development
opportunities and guaranteed work. And
then we're augmenting through contractor
work that again we're guaranteeing the
work based on the fact that we've got a
dedicated build that we're fully
committed to.
>> There's a bunch of questions. hopefully
um you can get back to these folks um
afterwards. But gee, you know, I've
always been so impressed um with your
work and I really appreciate your light
talk at our conference last year. It was
amazing and thank you guys. Thank you
for spending your time with us today and
sharing your insight and knowledge and
really excited for what you guys are
doing with Vidinium Fiber. I I want to
thank everybody for joining us today and
look forward to getting back together
next Wednesday with Jim Martin, the
president CEO of City discuss bridging
the divide in the mountain state, city
net's role in rural broadband expansion.
So thanks for that. And I also just want
to shout out to all the state broadband
offices. Um just know you guys are
working your ass off to September 4th.
So we're we're thinking about you every
day and um appreciate all the hard work
you guys are doing. Thanks everyone.